A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Multimedia Material, Accession 2017:067 FA1320
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Multimedia Material, Accession 2017:067
1950-2008
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1320
1.07 Cubic Feet 3 boxes: 1 legal document container, 1 letter document container, 1 4x6 card file box
Related Materials
Related to material in Boxes 99-107 in Ford Foundation records, Publications (Non-Grant Related), Accession 2017:050
Arrangement
Materials are arranged as received from the Ford Foundation in 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2017 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2017:067.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Separated Materials
Special format items have been separated from the body of the collection and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
Scope and Contents
Ford Foundation records, Multimedia Material, Accession 2017:067 contains photographs, negatives, slides, and films related to Ford Foundation press materials, publications, and projects, including the 1991 and 1992 Annual Reports, international women's programs in the 1980s, and activities of the Fund for Adult Education.
The collection also houses microfiche of press releases and responses, newspaper clippings, editorial round ups, and annual reports.
Ford Foundation
- Multimedia Material, 1; 1.07 Cubic Feet 3 boxes: 1 legal document container, 1 letter document container, 1 4x6 card file box
  - Innovations in State and Local Government - Photo Shoot (Photocopies of Originals), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Photocopies of original photographs include: Georgia No-Tillage Assistance Program, The Blackstone Project: Preventing Pollution Before It Happens, KET - Kentucky, schoolchildren, mural painting, babies with mothers, Seattle Neighborhood Matching Fund, exhibit layout, K-6 Fresno, Trauma Intervention Program, Friends of the Family, School-Based Youth Services NJ, Philadelphia Anti-Graffiti Network, Monroe Maternity Center
  - 1991 Annual Report Photo Research - ORI Photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Photographs by Bob Stockfield and photo captioned, "The Foundation supports analysis of current trends in Europe and their effects on groups like NATO" and on back "Military - NATO Exercises in Germany, NATO, Randy G. Taylor/Gamma-Liason"
  - 1991 Annual Report Photo Research - International Affairs Photographs, 1978-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    United Nations Interim Force in Lebanon - 1978, 1980; World Summit for Children, United Nations Headquarters - 1990
  - 1991 Annual Report Photo Research - Education & Culture Photographs, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Antony Gormley's Installation in the Old City Jail; 1990 Los Angeles Festival - Bread and Puppet Theater Performance from Vermont
  - 1991 Annual Report Photo Research - Rights & Social Justice Photographs (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Notes on back of photos: Gabra - N. Kenya - Millenium; Nyimba, N.W. Nepal - Woman with 4 Husbands Ages 8-30 - Millenium; #13-34: Mzarabani Communal Land
  - 1991 Annual Report Photo Research - Governance & Public Policy Photographs (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Photos from "In the Shadow of Love: A Teen AIDS Story" - Afterschool Special on ABC produced by WGBH Boston
  - 1991 Annual Report Photo Research - Rural Poverty Photographs, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contains photos, slides, and negatives of the Cache River in Illinois and farming in Bangladesh and Nigeria
  - 1991 Annual Report Photo Research - Urban Poverty Photographs (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Photos by Marc PokKempner - Chicago; Christopher Morris, 1990 Black Star, Mexico; 70M Rio Branco Distributed by Magnum, Brazil, Sao Bernardo S. P.; Ken Ross - Slum Village, Rio, Brazil
  - 1992 Annual Report - United Nations Photographs, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Titles of photographs include: United Nations Interim Force in Lebanon; United Nations Peace-Keeping Force in Cyprus; Secretary-General of Environment and Development Conference Introduces Pele as Goodwill Ambassador; Press-Conference by Secretary-General of Conference of Environment and Development; Human Settlements - The Places Where People Live and Work, Beijing, China and Dacca Bangladesh; United Nations – Sponsored News Mission Visits Middle East, May 1983, In Connection with the International Conference on the Question of Palestine, Quneitra, Syria; Communications is for People: World Communications Year, Sichuan Province, China, 1982; Farming for Development: Agriculture in China, Sichuan, China; Population and Family Planning, Dacca, Bangladesh; Refugees in Somalia; National Forest Inventory in Mexico, Durango, Mexico; Energy in the 21st Century/The Alternatives, Sichuan, China, 1979; United Nations Interim Force in Lebanon (UNIFIL); Secretary-General Visits Untag Military Headquarters in Namibia, Sviderhof Base, Namibia
  - 1992 Annual Report - Photocopies of Photographs from the Bettman Archive/Bettman Newsphotos/United Press International (UPI) and Reuters Photo Libraries (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Photocopies of agricultural scenes, international affairs, picket lines, women breaking barriers, scenes of life under communism, UNICEF, urban and rural poor, refugees, and migrant workers
  - 1992 Annual Report - Photographs, Slides, and Negatives, 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Photograph captions/titles include: Hispanics in the market of Paseo de la Plaza in Los Angeles defy cultural and political labels; Press Conference by President of Costa Rica, United Nations, New York; Farming for Development - Nepal; Coping with Disaster: Drought in Ethiopia; Coping with Disaster: Nicaraguan Refugees in Honduras; Drought in Africa, Korem, Ethiopia; Millenium - Nigeria, Brazil, Philippines; UNICEF - Nigeria slides; includes negatives
  - Women's Programs - Photographs of Working Women - South Africa, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Women's Programs - Photographs - India, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Note from Original Envelope: Addressed to: Ms. Nancy Boggs; From: Viji Srinivasm; Subject: Women's Programs: Slides and Photographs; Date 23 May 1985; The Ford Foundation, 55, Lodi Estate, New Delhi 3
    Photograph 1. Grantee: Annapurna Mahila Mandal, Description: Home-based caterer kneads dough for migrant workers, Intervention: Centralised workshop for middle-class clientele; Photograph 2. Grantee: Working Women's Forum, Description: Flower-vendor selling flowers, Intervention: Access to credit and direct linkage with flower-growers; Photograph 3. Grantee: Working Women's Forum, Description: Home-based producer rolling incense-sticks, Intervention: Child labourer education centre; Photograph 4. Grantee: Working Women's Forum, Description: Home-based producer rolling incense-sticks, Intervention: Access to credit and new markets; Photograph 5. Grantee: Working Women's Forum, Description: Home-based producer rolling incense-sticks, Intervention: Child care and health centre; Photograph 6. Grantee: Working Women's Forum, Description: Home-based producer makes lace, Intervention: Access to credit, empowerment through organising; Photograph 7. Grantee: Vanvasi Seva Kendra, Description: Traditional looms of women's blanket-weavers, Intervention: Upgrading looms at Women's Development Centre; Photograph 8. Grantee: Community Services Guild, Description: Food Stall, Intervention: Access to credit; Photograph 9. Grantee: Community Services Guild, Description: Cleaning of millet on payment of a small wage, Intervention: Access to credit to buy large quantities and clean and sell when prices are high; Photograph 10. Grantee: Mahila Sewa Trust, Description: Girls learning pottery, Intervention: Non-traditional occupations for women; Photograph 11. Grantee: Mahila Sewa Trust, Description: Junksmith, Intervention: Access to credit, skill training and upgrading; Photograph 13. Grantee: Master Craftsmen's Association of Mithila, Description: Paintings in Madhubani Style, Intervention: Central workshop and storage facilities
  - Women's Programs - Slides - Self Employed Women's Association (SEWA), Ahmedabad, India, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Note from original envelope: Handiraft workers, block printers (sp?), market workers, cigarette rollers, cart puller
    Photographs copyright Joseph S. Viesti 1982; Captions include: SEWA Clothing Market, SEWA Handcart Pullers, SEWA Market Worker, SEWA Cigarette Roller, SEWA Handicraft Worker, SEWA Market
  - Women's Programs - Photographs from the Third Latin American and Caribbean Feminist Encounter, Mulherio Communications Center, SOS Corpo, Women's Health Group, and the Professional Association of Domestic Workers, Brazil Office, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Note from original envelope: Brazil Office - To: Gerry Whittington, Reports; From: Kathryn Burns; Contents: Material for Trustees' Meeting
  - Women's Programs - Negatives, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    2 negatives
  - Women's Programs - Bangladesh Women's Health Coalition Photographs, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Most photographs from the rural clinic in Bolora; Photo captions include: Coalition Clinic, Bolora; Coalition Sewing Center Tangail; BWHC Central Office
  - Women's Programs - Andean Region and Southern Cone Photographs, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Women's Exhibit - 1st Round Selection Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Photographs of famous women reproduced from Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe College
  - Women's Programs - Mexico - Negatives, Slides, and Photographs, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Oxford University - Sudan Slides - Ahfad University for Women, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Women's Programs - Income Generation & Legal Aid - Jakarta - Java Slides, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Staff Briefing Led by Professor Abdullahi An-Na'im, Resident Scholar, Everything You Wanted to Know about Islam, Human Rights, Religious Pluralism but were too Afraid to Ask, WKMProductions (DVD), 2007 December 6 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy currently unavailable. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist
  - CVS Photo CD Contact Sheet and Negatives - Unidentified Office Space, Buildings, 2008 June (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Access copy currently unavailable. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
  - CVS Photo CD - Unidentified Office Space, Buildings, 2008 June (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ford Grant Project CD - Iron Mountain Cover, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Fund for Adult Education (FAE) - League of Women Voters - "Government in Action" - Indiana University - Slides and Key to Slides, 1961 (?) (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Slides 1-9: USA 1961 - The Nation and its Government, Lynton K. Caldwell; Slides 10-13: The New Federalism - Intergovernmental Relations in the 1960s, Brevard Crihfield; Slides 14-26: Local Government and the Growing Problems of Urbanism, York Y. Willbern; Slides 27, 28: Processes of Policy Formulation - Political Action, David R. Derge; Slides 29-31: Processes of Policy Execution - Executive Action, John E. Stoner; Slides 32-38: Processes of Policy Control Legislative Surveillance and Judicial Action, Charles S. Hyneman; Slides 39-43: The Organization and Management of Public Agencies, William J. Siffin; Slides 44-55: Government in Action; The Public Bureaucracy, Paul Van Riper; Slides 56-59: The Budget and Public Finance, Donald H. Clark
  - Photos of Staff with Franklin Thomas at His Last Holiday Party, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Organized by individual staff names
  - Wanted: Men...Who Know Economics, Who Understand, Who Can Analyse, Who Can Express Themselves, Chamber of Commerce of the United States, Washington, D.C., undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Separated Materials
    Separated from film reel no. 620 "Room for Discussion"
  - Art Prints, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    1.) Vernet, J., View of Capo Miseno, 1740-45; 2.) Vernet, J., View of the Temple of Saturn, 1740-1745; 3.) Vernet, J. View of the Churches on the Caelian Hill 1740-1745; 4.) Vernet, J., View of the Ruins of the Temple of Diana..., 1740-1745; 5.) Vickers, A. G., Church of the Bonds of St. Peter; 6.) Vickers, A. G. The Moskoi Gate, Kremlin, Moscow; 7.) Vickers, A. G., Street Scene, Moscow; 8.) Vickers, A. G., View of Potsdam; 9.) Villon, J., Composition, 1959; 10.) Villon, J., Orly, 1962; 11.) Visentini, A., 1. Tempio della dea Vestale in Roma; 12.) Visentini, A., 2. Tempio della Sibbila Atiuoli; 13.) 3. Visentini, A. Faciata della Capela di S. Pietro Momtorio; 14.) Visentini, A. 4. Faciata della Prospetivo nel Palazo Spada in Roma; 15.) Visentini A. 5. Tempio dantonino e Faustina in Roma; 16.) Visentini, A. 6. Tempio di Nimes in Francia; 17. - 24.) Volpato and Ottaviani, Raphael's Loggias in the Vatican, 1772-1777; 25.) Ward, J., Burnt Rock; 26.) Whistler, J.A.M., Thames Police, 1859; 27.) Wilkie D., A Study for the "Village Politicians"; 28.) Yosiharu, The Great Foreign Elephant; 29.) Letter from Raymond J. Smyke describing Map of Africa hanging in Ford Foundation office - originally attached to the back of the frame (Horton #26, no Ford # of the Moll, "English Map of Africa"); Also includes some artwork captions - 1.) #18/224 Antiphonal Leaf: The Annunciation; 2.) 26 Antiphonal leaf: The Adoration of the Magi; 3.) #125 Carte nouvelle de la Mer Mediterranee; 4.) Raphael's Loggias in the Vatican
  - Foundation Clipping File/Microfiche Memo, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Originally with cards in Box 3
  - Press Release Responses and Clippings - Microfiche - 1-293, 1950-1966 (Box 3)
    Clippings organized chronologically by program
  - Press Release Responses and Clippings - Microfiche, 1967-1973 (Box 3)
  - FY 74 Clippings - Microfiche - 1-11, 1974 (Box 3)
  - FY 75 Clippings - Microfiche - 1-8, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Editorial Roundups - 263-284 - Microfiche, 1957-1972 (Box 3)
  - Editorial Roundups - Microfiche, 1967-1972 (Box 3)
  - Microfiche #1000-1001 - (Illegible) and Rotary, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - The Ford Foundation - Press Clippings - Annual Report 1951 to 1957 - Microfiche, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - The Ford Foundation Newspaper Clippings 1956: College Teacher's Salaries - No.1 & 2 - Microfiche (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ford Foundation, 1974 Annual Report - 2 parts - Microfiche (Box 3)
  - Guide to Foundation Annual Reports on Film - Microfiche, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Editorial Round Ups 1967, No. 46 - Microfiche (2 copies) (Box 3)
  - Reel No. 620 Room For Discussion - Film, undated; 2017:067:009 (Box 2, Item 2017:067:009)
    Special format items have been separated from the above listed file and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Reel No. 698 How to Organize A Discussion Group - Film, undated; 2017:067:010 (Box 2, Item 2017:067:010)
  - Reel No. 699B - How to Conduct a Discussion - Film, undated; 2017:067:011 (Box 2, Item 2017:067:011)
  - Franklin Thomas - Philadelphia Council on Foundations (COF) Annual Conference - Cassette Tape - Audio, 1981 May 14; 2017:067:012 (Box 2, Item 2017:067:012)